# Matthew K. Perez

Email: mkperez@umich.edu | Phone: (808) 286-4393 Website: https://matthewkperez.com/

#### RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interests involve leveraging human speech for characterizing health, behavior, and mood using machine learning models. My research has touched on various topics, including automatic speech recognition, grapheme to phoneme conversion, acoustic feature analysis, and computational paralinguistics. My thesis work largely involves developing novel approaches to enable individuals with speech impairments to communicate effectively, which has driven my passion for advancing the field of speech technology to benefit a broader range of populations.

# **EDUCATION**

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering Advisor: Dr. Emily Mower Provost	2017 – 2023 ( <i>expected</i> )
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor M.S. in Computer Science and Engineering	2017 – 2019
University of Notre Dame B.S. in Computer Science, Cum Laude	2013 – 2017
AWARDS  NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP)  GEM Ph.D. Engineering Fellowship  Dean's List, University of Notre Dame Balfour-Hesburgh Scholar, University of Notre Dame	2020 - 2023 $2019 - 2020$ $2015 - 2017$ $2013 - 2017$

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Computational Human Artificial Intelligence (CHAI) Lab

2017-Present

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI

My thesis is centered on developing automatic methods for those with disordered speech impairments. Projects span topics such as: accessible speech recognition, automatic paraphasia detection, and analysis tools for disease classification and severity estimation.

## **Research Assistant: Mobile Computing Lab**

2015-2016

University of Notre Dame

Notre Dame, IN

Investigated speech analysis methods for classifying mild traumatic brain injuries (concussions). I helped develop a tablet-based app for eliciting and analyzing speech tasks.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Research Intern** (Speech Synthesis Team)

2022

Google

Mountain View, CA

Finetuned large, self-supervised speech models for end-to-end, multimodal grapheme-to-phoneme (g2p) modeling. I showed that multilingual training improved model performance across multiple languages with significant performance improvements for low-resource languages.

## **Research Intern** (Speech/Signals Team)

2021

Cogito Corporation

Virtual

Researched novel approaches for multimodal fusion in large transformer-based models for speech emotion recognition. This work showed that modeling paralinguistic events such as silence within a BERT language model can lead to improved emotion recognition performance.

**Research Intern** (Bioengineering Tech Systems Group)

MIT Lincoln Laboratory

Lexington, MA

Researched speech-based articulation features for identifying across sets of neurological diseases (i.e. Parkinson's depression, Huntington's). The results showed there was an acoustic bias present in separate datasets which the articulation features were capturing.

**Software Engineer Intern** (*iOS team*)

2016

2019

Garmin

Olathe, KS

Contributed to the development of the Garmin iOS application, which syncs wearable device data to/from the iPhone. Specifically, implemented *Today Extensions* for the Garmin Connect Mobile app, which displays wearable health information like steps, activities, etc. I presented work to research teams and company executives.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Matthew Perez**, Duc Le, Amrit Romana, Keli Licata, Elise Jones, Emily Mower Provost. "Seq2seq models for automatic paraphasia detection". Transactions on Audio, Speech, and Language (In-submission)

Yang Yu, **Matthew Perez**, Ankur Bapna, Fadi Haik, Siamak Tazari, Yu Zhang. "PronScribe: Highly accurate multimodal phonemic transcription from speech and text". Interspeech 2023

James Tavernor, **Matthew Perez**, Emily Mower Provost. "Episodic Memory For Domain-Adaptable, Robust Speech Emotion Recognition". Interspeech 2023

**Matthew Perez**, Mimansa Jaiswal, Minx Niu, Cristina Gorrostieta, Matthew Roddy, Kye Taylor, Reza Lotfian, John Kane, Emily Mower Provost. "Mind the gap: On the value of silence representations to lexical-based speech emotion recognition". Interspeech 2022.

Amrit Romana, Minxue Niu, **Matthew Perez**, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Enabling Off-the-Shelf Disfluency Detection and Categorization for Pathological Speech". Interspeech 2022.

**Matthew Perez**, Amrit Romana, Noelle Carlozzi, Praveen Dayalu, Jennifer Ann Miner, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Articulatory Coordination for Speech Motor Tracking in Huntington Disease" Interspeech 2021.

Amrit Romana, John Bandon, **Matthew Perez**, Stephanie Gutierrez, Richard Richter, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Automatically Detecting Errors and Disfluencies in Read Speech to Predict Cognitive Impairment in People with Parkinson's Disease". Interspeech 2021

Zakaria Aldeneh, **Matthew Perez**, and Emily Mower Provost. "Learning Paralinguistic Features from Audiobooks through Style Voice Conversion" NAACL 2021.

**Matthew Perez**, Zakaria Aldeneh, and Emily Mower Provost. "Aphasic Speech Recognition using a Mixture of Speech Intelligibility Experts" Interspeech 2020.

**Matthew Perez**, Wenyu Jin, Duc Le, Noelle Carlozzi, Praveen Dayalu, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Classification of Huntington's Disease Using Acoustic and Lexical Features." Interspeech 2018.

Louis Daudet, Nikhil Yadav, **Matthew Perez**, Christian Poellabauer, Sandra Schneider, Alan Huebner. "Portable mTBI Assessment Using Temporal and Frequency Analysis of Speech." IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics 2017.

# **TALKS**

Google-Speech Reading Group, Mountain View	2022
The National GEM Consortium Technical Workshop, Virtual	2020
Graduate Engineering Research Symposium, Ann Arbor (Student Poster Award)	2018
SERVICES	
Reviewer, Transactions on Audio, Speech and Language Processing	2023
Reviewer, Transactions of Affective Computing	2023
Reviewer, Affective Computing & Intelligent Interaction (ACII)	2021
Reviewer, Computer Speech & Language	2020
Poster Chair, Michigan AI Symposium	2019